Jenny Leopoldina Smith, MSc

Email: JennyL.Smith12@gmail.com **Website:** jennylsmith.github.io

Code: github.com/jennylsmith Linkedin.com/in/jenny-leopoldina-smith

Computational biologist and R programmer applying methods in data science and data engineering to biomedical research. Expertise of over 8 years in genomics and next generation sequencing (NGS) data.

Work Experience

Computational Biologist, Senior April 2022 – Sept 2024

Seattle Children's, Seattle, WA Research Scientific Computing Dept.

- Developed and adapted reproducible genomics workflows using Nextflow and nf-core tools for RNA-seq quantification, Cut&Run, ATAC-seq, and PacBio Isoseq; enabled use of containerized software with singularity/apptainer and the PBSpro and SLURM executors on a high-performance compute cluster (HPC).
- Analysis and visualization of multi-sample scRNA-seq and scATAC-seq datasets with Cellranger quantification, followed by doublet detection, ambient DNA correction, dataset integration (SCANVI and Seurat v4/v5). Production of multiomics analyses for bulk transcriptomic and single-cell datasets using dplyr and tidyverse principles.
- Generation of complex visualizations include heatmaps, circos plots, oncoprints, 3D scatter plots, genomic tracks, network graphs, and volcano plots, among others, to identify actionable insights from multivariate biological datasets from NGS and public databases (ensembl, UCSC, Genomic Data Commons).
- Engagement in bioinformatics support by providing guidance and troubleshooting assistance at office hours and teaching internal courses.

Bioinformatics Analyst January 2017 – March 2022

Fred Hutchinson Cancer Center, Seattle, WA Principal Investigator: Dr. Soheil Meshinchi

- Developed Nextflow pipelines using docker for cloud computing on AWS and with singularity for on-prem HPC; processed 1000's of RNA-seq samples for gene expression quantification and fusion detection.
- Established a lab github organization at github.com/Meshinchi-Lab.
- Created an R package (DeGSEA) using Roxygen and 'usethis' framework to streamline the association of clinical covariates and RNA-seq expression data.
- Profiled pediatric AML subtypes defined by gene fusions and mutations using RNA-sequencing with supervised and unsupervised clustering ML algorithms, statistical regression and classification, in a multidisciplinary environment with biologists, bioinformaticians, clinicians, and lead investigators.

Postbaccalaureate Fellow June 2014 - June 2016

National Institutes of Health, *Bethesda*, *MD Principal Investigator:* Dr. Maria Morasso

• Investigated the function of homeodomain protein DLX3 in keratinocytes at NIAMS. Bioinformatics analysis of ATAC-seq and ChIP-seq (peak calling, motif enrichment, NGS.plot, Deeptools) from knock-out murine models.

Languages and Software

- R programming: base R, Tidyverse, Bioconductor, R package development, Quarto, Rmarkdown
- Bash/linux shell scripting
- Nextflow: DSL2 workflows, nf-core tools
- Python: scripting,
 Snakemake, Scanpy
- Git version control
- **Github** and bitbucket
- PBS/SLURM HPC schedulers
- Containerization: docker, singularity, apptainer
- Amazon Web Services: AWS S3 and Batch
- **Jira** and agile framework, Atlassian products
- CI/CD with Bamboo

NGS Data Types

- scRNA-seq (single-cell)
- scATAC-seq (single-cell)
- RNA-seg Illumina, PacBio
- ATAC-sea
- miRNA-seq
- Cut&Run
- ChIP-seq

Bioinformatics Analysis

- scRNA-seq and scATAC-seq differential expression and celltype classification
- RNA-seq differential expression
- RNA-seq Fusion detection
- RNA-seq long reads (PacBio)
- DNA Motif analysis

Jenny Leopoldina Smith, MSc

Email: JennyL.Smith12@gmail.com **Website:** jennylsmith.github.io

Code: github.com/jennylsmith **LinkedIn:** linkedin.com/in/jenny-leopoldina-smith

Education

Applied Bioinformatics and Genomics, M.Sc.

University of Oregon, Eugene, OR

June 2016 – September 2017

Biology, B.A., magna cum laude University of San Diego, San Diego, CA

August 2008 - May 2012

Genome wide differential binding and accessibility

- DNA variant calling
- Genomic alignments
- NGS quality control

Continuing Education and Volunteering

- 2024 POSIT Conference, DevOps for Data Scientists, Seattle, WA
- 2024 Nextflow NF-Core Hackathon, University of Washington
- 2024 IGNITE speaker to promote gender equity in STEM, Seattle Children's
- 2023 2024 International Society for Computational Biology (ISCB) member
- 2018 2023 RLadies event organizer, Seattle, WA
- 2022 Bioconductor conference organizer, Seattle, WA
- 2021- 2022 Mentor, UO Bioinformatics and Genomics Graduate Program
- 2021 SnpReportR, Carnegie Mellon and DNAnexus Hackathon
- **2020** Pacific Biosciences Isoseq3 analysis training
- 2020 Nextflow workflow development training
- 2017-2019 Women In Biology, MAPS Mentorship Group
- 2018 ConsensusML, NCBI Hackathon
- 2018 Mentor, Fred Hutch High School Internships

Publications

- Bertrums, E. J. M.*, Smith, J. L.*, Harmon, L.*, ... Meshinchi, S. Comprehensive molecular and clinical characterization of NUP98 fusions in pediatric acute myeloid leukemia. *Haematologica*. 2023. DOI:10.3324/haematol.2022.281653
- Farrar, J. E., Smith, J. L., Othus, M., ... Meshinchi, S. Long Noncoding RNA Expression Independently Predicts Outcome in Pediatric Acute Myeloid Leukemia. *Journal of Clinical Oncology*. 2023. DOI:10.1200/jco.22.01114
- Le, Q., Hadland, B., Smith, J. L., Leonti, A., ... Meshinchi, S. CBFA2T3-GLIS2 model of pediatric acute megakaryoblastic leukemia identifies FOLR1 as a CAR T cell target. *Journal of Clinical Investigation*. 2022. DOI:10.1172/jci157101
- Huang, B. J., Smith, J. L., Farrar, J. E., ... Meshinchi, S. Integrated stem cell signature and cytomolecular risk determination in pediatric acute myeloid leukemia. *Nature Communications.* 2022. DOI:10.1038/s41467-022-33244-6
- Smith, J.L., Ries, RE, Hylkema, ... Meshinchi, S. Comprehensive Transcriptome Profiling of Cryptic CBFA2T3-GLIS2 Fusion-positive AML Defines Novel Therapeutic Options – A COG and TARGET Pediatric AML Study. Clinical Cancer Research. 2019. DOI: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-19-1800

Additional Publications: https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0402-2779

Speaker Presentations

- IGNITE, panelist on careers in data science and technology to promote gender equity and representation in STEM. IGNITE Field Trip with Rainier Beach High School (Seattle Children's Research Institute, 2024)
- Molecular Medicine Tri-conference, panelist on AI in Genomics and Precision Medicine (San Francisco, CA, 2020).
- American Society for Hematology, oral presentation on Comprehensive Transcriptome Profiling of Cryptic CBFA2T3-GLIS2 Fusion-Positive AML Defines Novel Therapeutic Options — a COG and Target Pediatric AML Study (San Diego, CA, 2018).
- American Society for Hematology, oral presentation on The LSC17 Leukemic Stem Cell Signature Predicts Outcome in Pediatric Acute Myeloid Leukemia. Abstract Achievement Award Recipient (Atlanta, GA, 2017).